Let's go back to 1957.
让我们回到1957年
Representatives from six European countries
六个欧洲国家的代表
had come to Rome
来到罗马
to sign the treaty that was to create the European Union.
签署成立欧盟的条约
Europe was destroyed.
世界大战起于欧洲
A world war had emerged from Europe.
使欧洲惨不忍睹
The human suffering was unbelievable
人民承受着难以想象
and unprecedented.
和前所未有的苦难
Those men
那些代表
wanted to create a peaceful,
想建立一个和平
democratic Europe,
民主的欧洲
a Europe that works for its people.
一个为欧洲人运作的欧洲
And one of the many building blocks
该和平项目中的
in that peace project
一个组成部分
was a common European market.
就是建立欧洲共同市场
Already back then,
早在那时
they saw how markets,
他们就已知道
when left to themselves,
如果不监管市场
can sort of slip into being just the private property
市场就会沦为大企业和联合集团的
of big businesses and cartels,
私有财产
meeting the needs of some businesses
只满足一些企业的需求
and not the needs of customers.
而非消费者的需求
So from our very first day,
所以，在1957年
in 1957,
从欧盟建立的第一天起
the European Union had rules
欧盟就制定规定
to defend fair competition.
来维持公平竞争
And that means competition on the merits,
也就是按水平竞争
that you compete on the quality of your products,
根据产品品质、价格
the prices you can offer,
服务
the services, the innovation that you produce.
和创新性来竞争
That's competition on the merits.
这就是根据水平竞争
You have a fair chance of making it on such a market.
在这样的市场，你有公平的机会崭露头角
And it's my job,
身为市场竞争事务专员
as Commissioner for Competition,
我的工作就是
to make sure that companies who do business in Europe
确保在欧洲做生意的企业
live by those rules.
遵守这些规范
But let's take a step back.
但退一步来看
Why do we need rules on competition at all?
为何我们需要这些市场竞争的规范？
Why not just let businesses compete?
为何不直接让企业自由竞争？
Isn't that also the best for us
对我们来说
if they compete freely,
企业自由竞争不是更好吗？
since more competition
因为竞争越激烈
drives more quality,
产品质量就越高
lower prices, more innovation?
价格也会降低，创新性更高
Well, mostly it is.
大多数情况下是这样
But the problem is that sometimes, for businesses,
但问题是，有时在企业间
competition can be inconvenient,
竞争会是个阻碍
because competition means that the race is never over,
因为竞争永远持续着
the game is never won.
没有结束的一天
No matter how well you were doing in the past,
不论你过去表现多好
there's always someone
总有某些人
who are out there wanting to take your place.
虎视耽耽想取代你
So the temptation to avoid competition
所以，避免竞争的诱惑
is powerful.
十分强大
It's rooted in motives as old as Adam and Eve:
这种深深植入人心的诱惑，和亚当夏娃一样古老：
in greed for yet more money,
贪婪更多财富
in fear of losing your position in the market
害怕失去在市场的地位
and all the benefits it brings.
和它带来的所有好处
And when greed and fear
当贪婪和恐惧
are linked to power,
与权力扯上关系
you have a dangerous mix.
就很危险了
We see that in political life.
这在政治中很常见
In part of the world,
在世上某处
the mix of greed and fear
贪婪和恐惧的组合
means that those who get power
意味着表示拥有权力的人
become reluctant to give it back.
不愿将权力交给他人
One of the many things
在我们的民主制度中
I like and admire in our democracies
我喜欢并钦佩的诸多优点之一，就是
are the norms
规定选民可决定
that make our leaders hand over power
领导人是否该
when voters tell them to.
交出权力
And competition rules can do a similar thing in the market,
在市场中，竞争规范有着相似的作用
making sure that greed and fear doesn't overcome fairness.
它确保贪婪和恐惧不会威胁到公平性
Because those rules mean
因为这些规范意味着
that companies cannot misuse their power to undermine competition.
公司不可滥用权力破坏竞争
Think for a moment about your car.
就拿你的车来说
It has thousands of parts,
它由数千个零件组成
from the foam that makes the seats
从座椅的海绵
to the electrical wiring to the light bulbs.
到电线，到灯泡
And for many of those parts,
对于许多这些零件
the world's carmakers,
世上的汽车制造商
they are dependent on only a few suppliers.
只依赖少数供应商
So it's hardly surprising
所以，那些供应商会被诱惑到
that it is kind of tempting for those suppliers
聚在一起定价格
to come together and fix prices.
这一点也不奇怪
But just imagine what that could do
但是想像一下，这么做
to the final price of your new car in the market.
对新车在市场上的最终价格有何影响
Except, it's not imaginary.
然而这些并非虚构
The European Commission
欧盟委员会
has dealt with already seven different car parts cartels,
已处理了七件不同车零件的垄断案例
and we're still investigating some.
还有一些案例我们仍在调查
Here, the Department of Justice
在这里，司法部
are also looking into the market for car parts,
也在调查车零件的市场
and it has called it the biggest criminal investigation
并称其为有史以来最大宗的
it has ever pursued.
刑事调查
But without competition rules,
但是如果没有竞争规范
there would be no investigation,
就不会有任何调查
and there would be nothing to stop this collusion from happening
也没办法阻止这种勾当
and the prices of your car to go up.
然后你轿车的价格就会飙升
Yet it's not only companies
破坏公平竞争的
who can undermine fair competition.
除了公司企业
Governments can do it, too.
还有政府机构
And governments do that when they hand out subsidies
政府发补贴给受青睐的少数时
to just the favorite few, the selected.
就已经在破坏公平竞争了
They may do that when they hand out subsidies --
政府发补贴给企业的时候
and, of course, all financed by taxpayers --
也可能破坏公平竞争
to companies.
当然，所有费用由纳税人买单
That may be in the form of special tax treatments,
这种破坏可能以特别税收待遇的形式出现
like the tax benefits
比如，赋税优惠
that firms like Fiat, Starbucks and Apple got
像菲亚特，星巴克和苹果这类大公司
from some governments in Europe.
在欧洲得到一些政府的税收优惠
Those subsidies stop companies from competing on equal terms.
这些补贴破坏了公司间的公平竞争
They can mean that the companies that succeed,
这意味着成功的公司
well, they are the companies that got the most subsidy,
是那些得到最多补贴的公司
the ones that are the best-connected,
也是最会搞关系的公司
and not, as it should be,
然而成功的公司应该是
the companies that serve consumers the best.
给消费者最好的服务的
So there are times when we need to step in
所以，我们得时不时介入
to make sure that competition works the way it should.
确保竞争依其原本的方式进行
By doing that, we help the market to work fairly,
这么做，我们帮助市场公平运作
because competition gives consumers the power to demand a fair deal.
因为竞争使消费者有权做公平的交易
It means that companies know that if they cannot offer good prices
这表示，如果公司企业 知道自己不能提供更好的价格
or the service that's expected,
或提供预期的服务
well, the customers will go somewhere else.
那么消费者就会另寻他处
And that sort of fairness is more important
这种公平性
than we may sometimes realize.
有时比我们认为的更重要
Very few people think about politics all the time.
很少人成天思考政治
Some even skip it at election time.
有些人甚至忽略选举活动
But we are all in the market.
但我们都置身于市场中
Every day, we are in the market.
每一天，我们都在市场里
And we don't want businesses to agree on prices in the back office.
我们不希望企业背地里制定统一价格
We don't want them to divide the market between them.
不希望他们在彼此之间分割市场
We don't want one big company
不希望一间大公司
just to shut out competitors
打压屏蔽其他对手
from ever showing us what they can do.
不给它们表现的机会
If that happens,
如果这种事发生了
well, obviously, we feel that someone has cheated us,
显然我们会感到被欺骗
that we are being ignored or taken for granted by the market.
被忽略或不被市场重视
And that may undermine not only our trust in the market
这不只危害我们对市场的信任
but also our trust in the society.
也危害我们对社会的信任
In a recent survey,
最近一项调查显示
more than two-thirds of Europeans
超过2/3的欧洲人
said that they had felt the effects of lack of competition:
感受到缺乏竞争的影响：
that the price for electricity was too high,
电费过高
that the price for the medicines they needed was too high,
所需的药价格也过高
that they had no real choice
如果他们想乘公交
if they wanted to travel by bus or by plane,
或搭飞机旅行，他们并没有真正的选择机会
or they got poor service from their internet provider.
他们互联网提供商给予差劲的服务等等
In short, they found that the market didn't treat them fairly.
简而言之，他们发现市场交易并不公平
And that might seem like very small things,
乍看之下，这些都是小事
but they can give you this sense
但它们可以给你一种
that the world isn't really fair.
这个世界并不公平的感觉
And they see the market, which was supposed to serve everyone,
他们看出本该是服务大众的市场
become more like the private property of a few powerful companies.
变得像少数大公司的私有财产
The market is not the society.
市场不是社会
Our societies are, of course, much, much more than the market.
我们的社会，当然比市场要大许多
But lack of trust in the market
但缺少对市场的信任
can rub off on society
会影响整个社会
so we lose trust in our society as well.
所以我们也对社会失去信任
And it may be the most important thing we have, trust.
信任是我们所拥有最重要的东西
We can trust each other if we are treated as equals.
我们如果受到公平对待，就会信任彼此
If we are all to have the same chances,
如果我们都有同样的机会
well, we all have to follow the same fundamental rules.
那么，我们必须遵守同样的基本规则
Of course, some people and some businesses are more successful than others,
当然，一些人和企业比其他人更成功
but we do not trust in a society
但如果在比赛开始前
if the prizes are handed out
就已颁发奖项
even before the contest begins.
我们就无法信任这个社会
And this is where competition rules come in,
这就是竞争规范要解决的问题
because when we make sure that markets work fairly,
因为当我们确保市场公平运行时
then businesses compete on the merits,
企业就会老老实实竞争
and that helps to build the trust that we need as citizens
这帮助我们建立人民所需的信任
to feel comfortable and in control,
让我们感到舒适 感到可以掌控我们的选择
and the trust that allows our society to work.
这种信任帮助使我们的社会运作
Because without trust, everything becomes harder.
因为没有信任，每件事就变得困难
Just to live our daily lives, we need to trust in strangers,
为了过好日常生活，我们必须信任陌生人
to trust the banks who keep our money,
信任保管我们钱财的银行
the builders who build our home,
盖我们房子的工人
the electrician who comes to fix the wiring,
来修电线的电工
the doctor who treats us when we're ill,
我们生病时所看的医生
not to mention the other drivers on the road,
更不用说路上的其他驾驶员
and everyone knows that they are crazy.
大家都知道他们很疯狂
And yet, we have to trust them
但我们仍需相信他们
to do the right thing.
会做正确的事
And the thing is that the more our societies grow,
我们的社会越是成长
the more important trust becomes
信任就越发重要
and the harder it is to build.
但也越难建立
And that is a paradox of modern societies.
这就是现代社会的矛盾之处
And this is especially true
这尤其表现在
when technology changes the way that we interact.
当科技改变我们的相处模式时
Of course, to some degree, technology can help us
某种程度上，通过评分系统
to build trust in one another with ratings systems and other systems
和其他系统科技可帮助我们
that enable the sharing economy.
建立对彼此的信任，开启共享经济
But technology also creates completely new challenges
但科技也带来前所未有的挑战
when they ask us not to trust in other people
科技要我们不去相信其他人
but to trust in algorithms and computers.
改而相信算法和计算机
Of course, we all see and share and appreciate
当然，我们都见证、分享和感激
all the good that new technology can do us.
新科技所带来的好处
It's a lot of good.
优点有很多
Autonomous cars can give people with disabilities new independence.
自动驾驶汽车让残障人士更独立
It can save us all time,
科技可随时帮助我们
and it can make a much, much better use of resources.
也可更有效率地使用资源
Algorithms that rely on crunching enormous amounts of data
依赖大数据的算法
can enable our doctors to give us a much better treatment,
可使医生给我们更好的治疗
and many other things.
还有许多其他好处
But no one is going to hand over their medical data
但没人会交出他们的医疗数据
or step into a car that's driven by an algorithm
或踏进一台由算法驾驶的车
unless they trust the companies that they are dealing with.
除非他们相信提供服务的公司
And that trust isn't always there.
这种信任并非无所不在
Today, for example, less than a quarter of Europeans
今日，不到1/4的欧洲人
trust online businesses to protect their personal information.
认为线上企业能保护个人信息
But what if people knew
但如果人们知道
that they could rely on technology companies
科技公司能公平对待自己
to treat them fairly?
会如何？
What if they knew that those companies
如果他们知道那些公司
respond to competition by trying to do better,
对待竞争的方式就是做得更好
by trying to serve consumers better,
更好地服务顾客
not by using their power
而不是滥用权力
to shut out competitors,
打压竞争对手
say, by pushing their services
比如，将他们的服务
far, far down the list of search results
远远推到搜寻结果列表之外
and promoting themselves?
只推销自己
What if they knew that compliance with the rules
假使他们知道
was built into the algorithms by design,
遵守规范是有意建立于算法之中
that the algorithm had to go to competition rules school
在它能运作之前
before they were ever allowed to work,
算法得先确保竞争规范被遵守
that those algorithms were designed
这些演算法是用来避免
in a way that meant that they couldn't collude,
不正当的勾结
that they couldn't form their own little cartel
不会暗箱操作
in the black box they're working in?
搞垄断的小集团
Together with regulation,
有了法规的帮助
competition rules can do that.
竞争规范可以实现这一点
They can help us to make sure
可以帮我们确保
that new technology treats people fairly
新的科技公平待人
and that everyone can compete on a level playing field.
人人都能以同等条件竞争
And that can help us build the trust
这也能帮我们建立
that we need for real innovation
真正创新所需的
to flourish
信任
and for societies to develop for citizens.
让社会的发展为人民服务
Because trust cannot be imposed.
因为信任不能强加于人
It has to be earned.
它必须要被赢来
Since the very first days of the European Union,
自60年前欧盟成立的
60 years ago,
头几天起
our competition rules have helped
我们的竞争规范已帮助
to build that trust.
建立市场信任
A lot of things have changed.
很多事改变了
It's hard to say what those six representatives
这六位代表会用智能手机做什么
would have made of a smartphone.
很难说
But in today's world,
但在今日的世界
as well as in their world,
和他们那时的世界
competition makes the market work for everyone.
竞争让市场为每个人运作
And that is why I am convinced
这也是为何，我深信
that real and fair competition
真正的公平的竞争
has a vital role to play
在建立我们所需的信任
in building the trust we need
来充分利用我们的社会时
to get the best of our societies,
发挥着重要的作用
and that starts with enforcing our rules,
这一切从执行我们的规范开始
actually just to make the market work for everyone.
让市场为每个人运作
Thank you.
谢谢
(Applause)
（掌声）
Bruno Giussani: Thank you.
吉萨尼：谢谢
Thank you, Commissioner.
谢谢您，专员
Margrethe Vestager: It was a pleasure.
韦斯塔格尔：我的荣幸
BG: I want to ask you two questions.
吉萨尼：我想请教您两个问题
The first one is about data, because I have the impression
第一个是关于数据，因为我总有个印象
that technology and data are changing the way competition takes place
认为科技和数据正改变竞争发生的方式
and the way competition regulation is designed and enforced.
和竞争法规设计与执行的方式
Can you maybe comment on that?
您能给些看法吗？
MV: Well, yes, it is definitely challenging us,
韦斯塔格尔：是的，这确实是一大挑战
because we both have to sharpen our tools
因为我们必须让我们的工具更先进
but also to develop new tools.
并同时开发新的工具
When we were going through the Google responses
在处理谷歌对我们
to our statement of objection,
反对声明的回应时
we were going through 5.2 terabytes of data.
总共经手了5.2兆兆字节的数据
It's quite a lot.
十分庞大
So we had to set up new systems.
所以，我们必须设立新系统
We had to figure out how to do this,
我们必须找出办法
because you cannot work the way you did just a few years ago.
因为你无法以几年前的方式运作
So we are definitely sharpening up our working methods.
所以我们必须精进工作的方式
The other thing is that we try to distinguish
另一件事是，我们试着分辨
between different kinds of data,
不同种类的数据
because some data is extremely valuable
因为有些数据非常可贵
and they will form, like, a barrier to entry in a market.
会形成进入市场的阻碍
Other things you can just -- it loses its value tomorrow.
其他一些数据 - 隔了一天就没价值了
So we try to make sure
所以我们确保
that we never, ever underestimate the fact
我们知道
that data works as a currency in the market
数据就如市场中的货币
and as an asset that can be a real barrier for competition.
也可能是阻碍竞争的资产
BG: Google. You fined them 2.8 billion euros a few months ago.
吉萨尼：您几个月前罚款谷歌28亿欧元
MV: No, that was dollars. It's not so strong these days.
韦斯塔格尔：不，是美元 美元最近不怎么强势
BG: Ah, well, depends on the --
吉萨尼：呃，是根据 -
(Laughter)
（笑声）
Google appealed the case. The case is going to court.
谷歌上诉了，所以这个案子会上法庭
It will last a while.
会花一些时间
Earlier, last year, you asked Apple to pay 13 billion in back taxes,
去年早些时候，您向苹果索取130亿的退税
and you have also investigated other companies,
您也调查了其他公司
including European and Russian companies,
包括欧洲和俄罗斯的公司
not only American companies, by far.
不单只有美国的公司
Yet the investigations against the American companies
然而，针对美国公司的调查
are the ones that have attracted the most attention
最引人注目
and they have also attracted some accusations.
同时也引来一些指控
You have been accused, essentially, of protectionism, of jealousy,
您被指控施行保护主义，嫉妒
or using legislation to hit back at American companies
以法律来攻击征服欧洲市场的
that have conquered European markets.
美国公司
"The Economist" just this week on the front page writes,
“经济学人”本周的头版写道
"Vestager Versus The Valley."
“韦斯塔格尔 vs 硅谷”
How do you react to that?
您如何回应？
MV: Well, first of all, I take it very seriously,
韦斯塔格尔：首先，我很严肃看待这事
because bias has no room in law enforcement.
因为执法是容不下偏见的
We have to prove our cases with the evidence and the facts
我们必须以证据，事实和法律体系
and the jurisprudence
来证明我们的案子
in order also to present it to the courts.
以便陈给法庭
The second thing is that Europe is open for business,
第二，欧洲是开放市场
but not for tax evasion.
而不是避税所
(Applause)
（掌声）
The thing is that we are changing,
重点是，我们不断在改变
and for instance, when I ask my daughters --
举个例子，我问我女儿 -
they use Google as well --
她们也用谷歌 -
"Why do you do that?"
“你们为什么用它？”
They say, "Well, because it works. It's a very good product."
她们说，“因为它好用啊，是很好的产品”
They would never, ever, come up with the answer,
她们不会这样回答：
"It's because it's a US product."
“因为这是美国的产品”
It's just because it works.
只是因为这个产品好用
And that is of course how it should be.
当然，原本就该是这样的
But just the same, it is important that someone is looking after to say,
同样的，关注你的人说以下的话也很重要
"Well, we congratulate you
“当你不断成长时“
while you grow and grow and grow,
”我们恭喜你“
but congratulation stops
”但若我们发现你利用职权“
if we find that you're misusing your position
”去伤害其他竞争者，不让他们服务消费者时“
to harm competitors so that they cannot serve consumers."
”恭贺就会停止“
BG: It will be a fascinating case to follow.
吉萨尼：这会是个有趣的例子
Thank you for coming to TED.
谢谢您来TED演讲
MV: It was a pleasure. Thanks a lot.
韦斯塔格尔：这是我的荣幸，谢谢
(Applause)
（掌声）